Now legendary across the world, it was
the last great Mayan city, Chetsanita.
Located in the southeastern state of
Yucatan in Mexico, this sprawling
cosmopolitan city attracted thousands of
[music] men and women in its heyday, as
much as Paris at the time.
>> It has opportunities. It's exciting.
This was the place to be.
>> The sublime pyramid of El Castillo
radiated.
>> When you would emerge from that
building, you were looking out over this
enormous [music] plaza. 20,000, 30,000
people. Whoever was the person wielding
that position would [music] have been
godlike themselves.
>> A pyramid that hides a strange secret at
its core.
>> A temple that's forbidden to the public.
The leader stood in this very spot to
receive energies from the celestial
world and the underworld. To the Mayas,
this spot is therefore the most sacred
place in all of
>> Chichinita
>> and a giant cave upon which it may have
been built.
>> If uh that is true, it's going to be the
foundational trade of all this city.
They must had done everything from that
[music] cenote and the archeological
elements there must contain valuable
[music] information to understand the
city. This city state was brutally ruled
by a powerful military guild that never
thought twice about spilling blood.
[screaming]
Literally, [music] you could stand here
and count the number of human
sacrifices. Uh probably in [music] this
case there would have been hundreds if
not a thousand or more skulls here.
>> From human sacrifices to ingenious
architecture, experts are about to take
you deep [music] within this incredible
citystate which marked both the zenith
and the downfall of one of history's
greatest civilizations.
By the 11th century AD in southeast
Mexico, Chetszanita had reached its
apex. It is the most powerful Mayan city
in all of Meso America.
Built in the heart of the jungle, the
city spreads over 3 km.
It includes dozens [music] of lavish
monuments.
Among
them is El Castillo, a pyramid standing
30 m high dedicated to the powerful
snake god Kukulan.
It represents the city's religious
center.
To the north lies the great ball court,
a 170 m long playing field where two
teams compete as part of bloody rituals.
Towering over the canopy [music] is El
Carakol, one of the first observatories
ever built by mankind.
Its unique architecture allows for
incredibly precise measurements of the
movements of the stars.
And finally, the Temple of the Warriors
[music] with its vast covered arcade and
its 200 columns headquarters the ruling
masters of Chetsanita.
It is a cosmopolitan city of nearly
50,000 inhabitants, [music] as much as
Paris at the time. A truly unique city
that hides a world of mysteries within
its heart.
It is built over a network of
underground tunnels that span kilome
and caves so deep that even oxygen is
sparse.
We are on the heart of earth. We are on
the underworld. We are on the dark side
of the universe. And yeah, this
represented [music] fertility. You know
um the modern Maya from Chiapa said that
the stallctites and sometimes are
dropping are the breasts of the earth.
They said that the stallag mites that
grow on the floor are the fallows and
when they get together and form a column
the earth is copulating to make life
happen. So here we are on the sanctum
santorum of maya religion and ritual and
and beliefs.
If Chetsanita was built on top of caves,
it's because they were essential to the
Mayas.
In their eyes, they represented the
world of the dead while also being the
source of life.
They were the stage for their bloody
ceremonies
and human sacrifices. when a priest
would use an obsidian blade to carve out
his victim's heart to satisfy the gods
and assure the city would prosper.
>> We have probably the earliest date in
Chenita from this cave. It's a piece of
charcoal in taken one of the on the mud
of one of the walls that they that
[music] the Maya built to seal the cave.
So probably a lot of the development of
Chuchen started on this very cave.
>> It was [music] hence from great depth
that the world's largest Maya city and
its incredible pyramids rose to
prominence.
The year was 500 AD.
In the heart of the Yucatan jungle on
wild virgin territory,
men built the first huts and christened
their new village.
No one knows where these first
inhabitants came from, but they were
part of the powerful Maya civilization
whose cities flourished from the
highlands of the Pacific coast to the
shores of the Caribbean Sea. Meanwhile,
to the west, the Mexican highlands were
dominated by the most powerful city in
Meso America, Teayot Tiwakan.
Choosing to build a city here was no
accident.
This vegetital desert, the porest
surface of which allows no lake or river
to form, is actually home to an abundant
source of fresh water,
the Cenote Cigrad.
[sighs]
This enormous natural reservoir is 60 m
wide and 40 m deep, formed by limestone
that eroded with rainwater.
a water source seen by the Mayas as a
gift from the gods.
>> I do believe that uh the first uh
builders of Chuchenita came here because
of the cenotees
and this one in particular the most
important sacred cenotees in the Maya
area. I believe this is the mother of
all cenotees. If we're talking about uh
ritualism, if we're talking about
cosmoggony, this cenote was used to give
offerings to the gods.
>> Many of the offerings which have been
found within the sacrificial cenote um
come from cities in the southern
lowlands. So it is very likely that
people went to Chichanita as pilgrims.
>> Pilgrims that would strengthen the ranks
of the Chichanita population.
>> [music]
>> And that's not all. Because 700 km away,
a terrible drought struck the Maya
plains.
Tika, Carakol, and Palenke, large cities
with tens of thousands of inhabitants,
experienced a mass exodus.
Their all powerful leaders couldn't
soothe the anger of the gods.
We are understanding in archaeology is
that communities, cities, villages are
not forever. So maybe these people had
to leave and they resettle a new place
to live.
>> So we see a general rise in the Yucatan
in general of cities and communities in
the period 7 to 8 8 to 900. Chichen was
one of these places.
>> With the big cities crumbling [music] in
the south and given its sacred cenote,
the odds were in Chetszanita's favor to
become a significant city.
As a new order [music] started to take
shape, it began to work its way to the
top.
Back in the 8th century AD, Chetsanita
only comprised a few basic structures
made of adobe and wood.
Competition was ferocious.
Ukal
130 km [music] to the west was leading
the way.
The city had undertaken an ambitious
architectural plan.
Temples, palaces, and [music] pyramids
were built to ensure its local
supremacy.
In the battle to be the best, Chikanita
had no choice. It had to start building.
The monumental [music] architecture is
something that human beings do. It
reinforces uh religious ideology. It uh
reinforces our identity as a people. Who
are we? But also it shows uh power to
build these things. The energy to do it,
the economic power to do it and also uh
the power of the state to uh create
these kinds of structures.
>> Buildings that unlike the people's
humble dwellings were made [music] to
last because the people of Chetsanita
had a highly desirable resource,
limestone.
A large deposit was found right outside
the city.
>> It looks like they were carving this uh
stone which it was going to be probably
a serpent head. Can you see the shape of
the serpent here? You can see the mouth,
the eye still visible somewhere.
But it looks like when they were walking
it, it breaks. So they leave it they
leave the work unfinished.
The hard work was not to extract it. The
hard work was to carry it all the way to
the site. You imagine how many people
they needed and a special technique.
Maybe they push this uh stone through
rolls of wood logs so it could be
manageable. But it's amazing to believe
the big city of Chichenita is built with
big pieces of stone like this one.
Without the help of pack animals and
using the sole strength of their arms,
the Mayas crossed the jungle carrying
the heavy stones for hundreds of meters.
That's how the first pyramid was built,
Elosario.
At 12 m high, it was built at top a 25 m
deep cave which is connected to the
temple by a staircase.
It's a symbolic doorway to the
underworld.
Further south, Las Monas, a 50 m long
complex was the heart of the city.
Its upper level was home to private
apartments reserved for the elite with
long narrow rooms.
The Mayas were not familiar with
keystones. The technique which
originated in the western world allows
to distribute weight along the length of
a supporting wall to create large open
vaults.
But the Mayas couldn't use corbelled
vaults to distribute the weight.
So even the elitist homes were cramped.
Such was the price of durability.
This construction system is extremely
durable. It's over 1,000 years old. We
can still see part of the paint that
decorated the walls. This is a sign that
their system worked perfectly. If their
civilization had continued to develop,
perhaps the Mayas would have figured out
the solution, much like the Western
world did.
Below buildings with impressive puke
style sculpted facads characteristic of
the region may well have housed the
city's most powerful members.
over the doorway this feathery kind of
solary ring that that's surrounding this
individual who's probably a [music]
highranking elite lord if not one of the
kings of Chichen.
So here the lord sits above in his
throne or in this feathery space that's
symbolizing an entrance into the
underworld or a sacred mountain.
A ruler used Las Monas as his palace.
A pediment over one of the doors is
inscribed with Maya hieroglyphics that
provide precious clues to [music] his
identity.
>> It's very common in Maya culture for the
buildings or rooms to be inscribed with
the name of their patron or the person
who is tasked with an important
ceremony.
Here
everything seems to indicate this was
someone very important back then. Kaku
Palaku,
>> the first ruler of Chetsanita,
a man believed by the Mayas to be a
living god
who also broke with the traditions set
by many kings before him.
It seems that power was shared by
Akopakal and Enil Corpole, his halfb
brotherther and probably different
members of a family. This may have been
a reaction to the experience of the
collapse of dynastic kingship in the
southern Maya lands. People didn't want
to make the same mistake and uh put
power on several individuals rather than
one.
Like their ancestors for thousands of
years before them, Kaku Pakal and his
family drew their power from the stars.
By day, as by night, they studied the
skies, closely, following the movements
of the moon and the sun.
Determining their cycles was an attempt
to interpret a divine message.
The movements of the stars is very
regular and [music] so their worship of
time is coming from this. They had a
Venus calendar. It was a very complex
elliptical orbit that was better than
ours. And you have priests up there
[music]
uh you know making notes, seeing things
for hundreds and hundreds of years.
[music] They're getting a real idea
about these stars which are also you
know deities. So you get to know more
and more and more. Now [music] that's
not science. This is prophecy. The
movements of the stars will [music]
tell you a lot about the future.
>> The Mayas believe their priests read
messages from the gods and the stars.
To establish their power, the Chetsanita
elite had a brilliant idea.
They built a spectacular edifice [music]
dedicated to the heavenly vault.
El Karakol,
one of the first observatories ever
built by mankind.
Erected over a large platform, this 18 m
wide and 28 m high tower overlooks the
treetops.
[music]
Inside are openings that look out in
every direction.
These openings allowed them to observe
the sunlight, the moonlight,
and specific planetary constellations on
the horizon. At night, at sunset, and at
dawn,
for example, from this doorway, the sun
traces a line between this opening and
the opposing opening on the other side.
That's how you know it's the winter
solstice on December 21st.
>> Heavily damaged, only three of the
original openings remain intact today.
The first is aligned with [music] the
astronomical south.
The second with the setting of the moon
on March 21st,
and the third faces the sunset on the
autumn [music] and spring equinoxes, as
well as the northernmost position of the
most sacred star in Maya culture, Venus.
People have argued that the Maya had the
original Star Wars because they used
Venus in order to uh uh predict when to
go to war and when not to. Venus was not
the goddess of love but uh a symbol of
of war.
And so observation was more than just
about the beauty of observing the sky.
It was about controlling people, [music]
controlling politics, uh controlling the
religious system. Uh, and so it's a
powerful tool.
>> On either side of the tower, two
trenches trace its curve
between 2 to 8 m deep. Their purpose
remains a mystery to archaeologists.
Recently, an engineer examining these uh
decided that they were probably bases
for moving screens. He argues that the
Maya would have used gears and wheels in
order to move these big wooden screens.
These two screens could have been
activated when needed.
Moving the screens would have allowed
for a greater number of precise
observations compared to using only the
naked eye.
If that's the case, that would have
provided another really uh powerful uh
source of um astronomical uh observatory
uh ability. Now again, that's
speculative and is not being published
or written up by archaeologists.
However, those ditches or those areas do
exist and uh an explanation is needed.
With its one-of-a-kind Maya Observatory
and all its lavish monuments, Cheetanita
quickly rose to power in less than a
century.
But there was one essential
developmental component the city was
missing.
control of precious commercial routes.
The masters thus launched an offensive
in the north near the port city of
Elessas Cerritos.
Chichen was investing not only here but
across a larger landscape in order to
develop and control trade. It couldn't
have done what it did without access to
the coast.
I think they were eliminating
competition. They would get control of
all the trade routes. I mean, I think
they were a predatory state. I mean,
they would get booty and all of that.
But if you look at what happened in the
the period, not very long period
afterwards or maybe even during um they
were extending a trade empire.
Their
conquests allowed Chetszanita to control
a territory of 100 km
and gave it direct access to the sea and
a strategically valuable resource
salt.
>> A lot of Meso America itself didn't have
access to salt. And in fact, Isla is
very close within a few miles of the
beginning of some of the most important
salt producing areas in Yucatan. So I
think it's pretty clear to me that
Chichchen was controlling the production
and distribution of salt as well. So it
was an important resource I believe uh
for the uh Chichen state.
>> Chichinita became the greatest economic
power in the region.
From easeless Cerritos, [music] canoes
loaded with precious merchandise could
reach all of Meso America.
It's a huge canoes and it's very
efficient. Why would you go so far? It's
by water, but what really makes it
efficient is you don't [music] have to
go through other kingdoms. We're going
to lots of trouble. You can swing out
into the oceans.
>> And what Chuch Chen did was in order to
acquire and move these luxury objects,
Chichen established coastal ports from
Bise to the Gulf of Mexico.
From the coast, Chichinita's merchants
went deep inland,
all the way to the Mexican highlands,
a journey that took them some,500 km
away to Tula, the powerful Toltech
capital.
The ensuing encounter was about to
completely transform Chichanita.
By the end of the 9th century,
Chichinita's influence had grown so
[music] much that thousands of people
migrated to the powerful city from all
four corners of Meso America.
>> It has opportunities. It's it's
attractive to people. It's exciting uh
politically, ideologically,
from a consumer perspective in terms of
goods and services, the city uh security
uh this was the place to be. And [music]
I think that in migration uh was part of
the process of the growth of the city.
>> To [music] welcome these new arrivals,
Chetsita needed to expand again.
the old city began to put up
scaffolding.
>> There's a time period where you start
seeing uh the influx of international
ideas. People start changing their
houses. People start [music] building uh
additions to their buildings and and
reconfiguring things.
Above all, the city's center moved north
where vast swaths of forest were cleared
to make place for new buildings.
When that happened, they didn't bring
the Stila. They brought to the new
center another way to depict or send a
message about authorities.
>> There's a sort of a big change in the
architecture, in [music] the murals, in
the religion, in that layout. And the
question is um what caused that?
Previously built in traditional Maya
style, the city began to radically
change its appearance,
in the new city center, one building
came to symbolize this new trend,
the temple of the warriors.
This 150 m long complex is made up of
several temples.
Its vast underground chamber supported
by 200 columns [music] is unique in the
Maya world.
Crowning the top, two sculptures of the
feathered serpent, a divinity that was
previously unknown in Chetsanita frame a
series of columns and bass relief
[music] warriors.
Archaeologists have long been intrigued
by these architectural choices.
the uh structure of the platform, uh the
central stairway, the use of columns in
front, this open space, uh the Venus
figures, uh the uh feathered serpents,
all of that is similar to what we see at
Tula. [music]
Tula's pyramid B in the former Toltech
capital inspired [music] the design of
Chetsanita's Temple of the Warriors.
[music]
A sidebyside comparison of the
blueprints of the two buildings reveals
an almost identical structure.
But what led to these [music] changes?
Why would the rising star of the Maya
era adopt these previously foreign
building codes?
>> For a long time, people have thought
that Chichona was conquered by troops
from Tula. I wouldn't say that is not
impossible. But whether this is evidence
for a direct overtaking of Ticha or
whether there was more like a common
style is something which is still under
heavy debate.
Whether a Toltech invasion took place or
not, there's no doubt that the two
cities are closely affiliated. Chetsita
adopted the codes of its distant Mexican
cousin.
A change in style that coincided with
the death of Kaku Pakal [music] and a
comprehensive reorganization of power in
the Maya city.
>> There's clearly [music] a shift in the
political organization. This divine king
is no longer celebrated.
Uh what we see is the celebration of
warriors.
So it's probably a place where the
social groups, the different warrior
societies came uh interacted, carried
out their official business. And it
probably was exciting for young men to
have an opportunity to publicly display
their military prowess and abilities. So
in some ways uh I think this was a place
where people could increase their social
status by participation.
The temple of the warriors became the
symbol of the new masters of Chetsanita.
A powerful guild [music] of soldiers
that plan to impose their will upon the
city and beyond.
Once admired, Chetsanita was now feared.
Military power was so much more
important at Chi-Chen than the Maya
centers and more organized. These
temples are temples of warrior guilds,
like unions. And so those they would
gather there and obviously they would
have a lot of power. And then what were
all these Chi-Chen people dressed up
like warriors with warrior gills? What
were they doing? You know, playing
chess. I It's war. [music]
>> [music]
>> What they were doing was in essence
building a military order in order to
carry out the socopolitical agenda of
the state. And part of that agenda was
waring against local communities,
terrorizing local communities, um
bringing in tribute from other towns and
communities around expanding the power.
The powerful Chetsa army bended the
neighboring cities to its will.
Ekbalam and Uk were vanquished.
>> The few survivors were bluntly herded to
the city.
>> Thrown into confinement cells, they
waited to be sacrificed.
Not far away was another prominently
located and highly visible building, the
Zoni, which was adorned with thousands
of carved skulls.
There are sticks going through the
skulls so that they would have actually
been uh if you had seen them, they're
depicting skulls one on top of the
other. So this is actually a basil
platform or a platform that would have
supported a large wooden rack and the
wooden rack would have been uh filled
with human skulls.
>> The prisoners didn't have long to wait.
One after another, [music] they were
offered to the gods.
They were beheaded swiftly [screaming]
>> and without ceremony
>> on these buildings. [music]
There are uh individuals that are
walking with trophy heads. So you can
see warriors actually holding the heads,
probably the heads that would have been
displayed on here. There are also
depictions of uh eagles and jaguars
holding human hearts, which suggests
that part of the ritual involved with
this would have uh entailed removing the
heart from these victims. So this is a
giant operation for human sacrifice. So
whoever would have come here both the
citizens, visitors, whomever would have
been able to see here a visible image of
the power of the state. Literally
[music]
you could stand here and count the
number of human sacrifices. Uh probably
in this case there would have been
hundreds if not a thousand or more
skulls here.
A macabra spectacle meant to remind all
of the fate that awaited Chetszanita's
enemies and which once again had Mexican
origins.
>> They don't have zantles everywhere.
They're quite rare in the Maya lands. A
Zanti is a symbol of sophistication.
It distinguishes Chi-Chen from other
Maya cities because Chi-Chen represents
[music] the pinnacle of this kind of
international culture,
internationalization that's going on
here.
But a reign of terror was not enough.
In this cosmopolitan city where cultures
and languages mixed together, everyone
has to be on board.
To that end, what better than a new
place of worship?
Dominating the main square, a pyramid 30
m high and 55 m wide became the new
religious center of Chetsanita.
El Castillo, a building at the service
of power.
You can imagine [music] this is a
theater. This pyramid doesn't sit like
back somewhere hidden. Everyone always
[music] thinks of this stairway because
when you would emerge from that
building, you were looking out over this
enormous [music] plaza. 10,000, 20,000,
30,000 people waiting for you to go in
and to come out.
Imagine dressed up as an ancient Maya of
Chichen rising up those stairs on those
days. The heavens, the universe is
interacting with you and with this
person. That's really powerful that
whoever was the person [music] wielding
that position of authority on the
landscape would have been close to the
gods if not godlike themselves.
>> Here thousands [music] of faithful
followers worship the new god of the
city,
Kukul Khan, the feathered serpent.
This being of Mexican origins was
believed to be the messenger of the gods
and the source of absolute power for he
who knew how to listen. Of all
Mesamerican deities, Kukul Khan is by
far the most enigmatic.
Some saw him as a supernatural being
while others believed he was a man of
flesh and blood.
Between myth and reality, the true
nature of this serpent god seems to have
been lost in the fog of history.
Did kukulan exist? I would say yeah.
It's a mixture of the human being and
divinity. The key thing is here is where
does the human being influence ends and
where does divine figure appear.
One of the issues surrounding uh the
relationship between Chichen and Tula
was always this idea that the feathered
serpent of the Toltk [snorts] uh was a
living person who at some point left
Tula and came south to [music] um
Chichen and founded the city. Now most
of us don't believe that anymore.
>> Why Kukon becoming such a um an
important deal? That's really does have
something to do with the connection with
Mexico. He's a big deal over there.
>> He may have been um a deity which was
regarded as a leader of the foreigners
or somehow associated with the
foreigners that came to Chichinitsa.
By dedicating El Castillo to Kukul Khan,
Chichinita's elite formed a powerful
bond between the Mayas and the
communities of central Mexico and
ushered in an era of social peace.
>> El Castillo thus became the most sacred
place in the city connected to the most
sacred star, the sun.
>> This building didn't just sit on the
landscape, it interacted [music] with
the landscape. particularly with the um
sun for example there are 91 stairs on
[music] each side with the top that's
365 so it's a space that is representing
the year
the solar cycle is at the heart of El
Castillo's mechanics
on the spring and fall equinoxes the sun
casts a shadow on the rail of the temple
staircase that reveals a serpent made of
night,
a magical spectacle that marks the start
and the end of the rainy season.
>> During the course of the [music] day
that as the sun moves the b the the
ballastrate actually looks like a
writhing serpent and uh in the morning
it comes down from the heavens and in
the evening it ascends back up into the
heavens. So these these ballast raids
are not simply architectural.
Again, they're cosmological, right?
Measuring time is at the heart of Maya
cosmology.
And in Chetsenita, El Castillo is the
key.
In 1930, archaeologists made an
incredible discovery.
By digging this tunnel through the side
of the temple,
[music] they discovered a second
pyramid. This one 16 m high and
structurally identical to El Castillo.
At its summit, in the belly of the Great
Pyramid, was an exceptional temple
forbidden to the public.
We learned that its construction was
tied to the way their calendar worked.
Every 52 years, the Mayas added a layer
to the structure.
We're here in the second one. And it's
very likely that beneath us lies the
first construction level of the
structure.
>> 52 years, a length of time that's far
from arbitrary
because the Mayas actually used two
calendars.
The Hob which is comprised of 365 days
symbolizing the solar cycle
and the Tolken a ritual calendar of 260
days divided into 13 months of 20 days
each.
Three wheels of time that synchronize
exactly every 52 years.
By building their pyramids like Russian
dolls, [music] the Mayas prevented
pillaging of the pyramid preceding El
Castillo,
a temple that hides one of the greatest
treasures of Meso America,
the red jaguar throne.
>> The jaguar is the symbol of the
underworld.
The leader stood in this very spot to
receive energies from above and below
from both the celestial world and the
underworld. To the Mayas, this spot
represents the most sacred place in all
of Chichinita, a place where only the
leader of the city was allowed to enter.
The [music] vertical axis of El Castillo
is the imaginary axis that unites the
kingdom of heaven and the kingdom of
darkness.
It's a sacred place with a carefully
chosen location
for El Castillo is located at the exact
intersection of the four cenotes that
surround the city.
Segrad in the north,
Cholok in [music] the south, Kuyum in
the east, and Holun to the west.
It's precisely here beneath El Castillo
that archaeologists are on the brink of
another incredible discovery.
Using electrodes, they [music]
discovered a 20 m high and 30 m wide
cavity a mere 5 m below the surface.
El Castillo was seemingly built on top
of an enormous cave.
Even though [music] there's a gap, even
though there is a void, the Maya knew
that the cast the soil could be thicker
in some areas. It might be the case
here. I believe my assumption is there
must be at the very least 5 m of
bedrock. Uh if you think about it, most
of these buildings are built over gaps,
over caverns, and they knew they could
build this one here.
>> Only new excavations will [music]
determine whether there really is a
fifth cote here.
a discovery that could provide [music]
precious new clues about the origins of
the city.
>> If uh that is true, which I believe it
is, it's going to be the foundational
trade of [music] all this city. They
must had done everything from that
cenote and the offering, the elements,
the archeological elements there must
contain [music]
valuable information to understand the
city. Obviously, if there's a cenote
underneath the pyramid, that's super
cool because that means that this
building is in fact sitting on the
direct portal to the underworld. We
haven't seen the cenote yet. And so, the
day that they show pictures of that
cenote uh will be a worldwide event.
>> The military elite of Chichinita had
completed their power conquest.
The city was in their hands and the
surrounding towns had been subjugated.
But in order to keep the peace, a social
outlet was needed.
To that end, what better way than a ball
game?
The elites of Chetsanita thus had an
enormous playing field built.
168 m long and 70 m wide. Its rings hung
some 9 meters off the ground.
Spectator stands were built on both ends
of the field
along with a temple for the upper class.
It was the biggest ball playing field
[music] ever built in Meso America.
The idea of building a ball court like
this is saying we're the most powerful
city state in Yucatan and there's no one
who could compete with us on the playing
field or building a playing field like
this. This is an important political
statement.
In this 2,000-year-old sport, two teams
battle on the field to score points by
sending the ball through the opposing
team's ring [music] without using their
hands.
Sports [music] are a way for society to
interact with each other without going
to war. Uh they can compete uh on the
playing field and I think that they were
doing that here.
If we're standing here, let's say 900,
950 AD, what you would see here, uh, is
not just this plain stone. All of this
stone would be covered in stucco. It
would be brightly painted, red, green,
blue, yellow. So that it would have
looked fantastic. And uh, you would have
probably had audience members sitting a
top the uh, this area here. important
personages at the ends of the ball court
[music] um feasting and uh calling out
to the ball players. This would have
been a massive celebration for an event
like this would be like the Super Bowl.
A game that players were handpicked to
play. But unlike American football, the
game ended very differently.
At the end of it, the losing players
were sacrificed.
If we were in medieval Europe, uh, like
jousting matches, these were the elites
that jousted. The masses [music] might
watch, but the people on the playing
field were the upper class. So, they're
not just sacrificing a poor peasant.
They're sacrificing a lord. I'm sure
there were people who did not agree, but
I think what was expected of you was to
agree. It's an honor to be sacrificed.
And in fact, it's essential for you to
be sacrificed because the idea of
rebirth and death, of fertility and
growth, all of these things are
connected to the sacrifice. So the ball
court [music] and the ball game are kind
of like a machine designed to make the
world go.
Although the city's inhabitants
thoroughly enjoyed the show, the gods
seemed indifferent to the bloodshed.
Because beneath the city, the water
reserves were dangerously dropping.
After just three centuries of existence,
the city began to run low on resources.
The priests increased the number of
ceremonies, invoking [music] Tlalok, the
god of the rain,
and made offerings in vain.
It looks like all this happened in a
time of drought. There was problems up
there. There was no rain.
So one hypothesis is we are desperate
for water. And by the end of the 11th
century, peasants could not harvest. So
maybe peasants were able to survive,
but they were unable to pay for the
taxes. And the first ones affected by
this were probably the elite.
>> Deprived of their subsidies, the city's
elites are said to have simply
disappeared. And along with them, the
administration, the bureaucracy, and
eventually the state.
Yet, not all archaeologists find this
explanation to be convincing.
>> This was a probably a difficult city to
manage. There were lots of different
people with lots of different values and
norms here compared to a typical Maya
center. U trying to keep them all
engaged and [music] connected to the
system uh may have been one of the
biggest challenges that they faced. One
of the things you think about is look at
the Soviet Union. There was no war. I
mean there was no calamity. There's no
aliens. There's no comet smashing
[music] and it just fell apart. And so,
um, systems can fail without major kinds
[music] of events causing them.
>> Was Chichinita the victim of a
disastrous climate [music] event? Or did
it crumble beneath its own weight?
No one knows.
One thing is certain, the powerful Maya
city has never ceased to fascinate
anyone who's been lucky enough to admire
its temples. After Chichinitsa collapsed
and was abandoned by the majority of its
population, it continued to serve as a
place for pilgrimage and it was never
forgotten by the local population. When
the Spaniards came in the 16th century,
one of the first settlements was
constructed over the ruins of
Chichinitsa.
>> And thus, the story of the last great
Maya city comes to an end. An
extraordinary city that marked the
zenith of a 4,000-year-old civilization.
One that continues to leave
archaeologists wondering.
Who knows what secrets the ancient Mayas
buried in the city's depths?
Who? hasn't dreamed of these
pre-Colombian temples,
of these faraway lands filled with
legends.
Who hasn't wanted to wander guided by
the sun through the heart of Maya
country?
Tiko, Guatemala.
This city, a genuine treasure of mankind
for over 2,000 years, has been
captivating visitors ever since it was
rediscovered in the 19th century.
The way they build these huge, tall,
incredible structures. Imagine these
buildings more than a thousand years and
they are still there. That's impressive.
>> But it wasn't until very recently that
experts [music] made astounding
discoveries thanks to state-of-the-art
technology.
An aerial laser system is undertaking a
scan of the jungle, revealing that
Tikall was once a sprawling sovereign
city comparable [music] to ancient Rome.
is the size of what is now Guatemala
City. And Guatemala City can host at
least between 3 to four million of
people.
>> At 70 m high, Temple 4, the second
highest pyramid ever built after Giza,
hosted gory sacrifices.
>> At its base, a hidden tunnel unveils the
secrets behind the extraordinary
ingenuity of the Maya [music]
civilization. You can like make jokes to
the Egyptian archaeologists when you see
them about their sad [music] little
pyramids.
>> A gigantic citadel buried some 10 km
from the city center.
Practical wars, a voracious appetite for
sacrifices, architectural genius, and a
mastery of science and astronomy.
All part of the Odyssey of Tikall, the
most bewitching Maya city and of its
builders. From its expansion to its
mysterious disappearance. Heat.
Heat.
[music]
750 AD,
in the heart of the deepest jungle of
the Patan region in northern Guatemala
rose The city state of Tikal, the
largest Maya city ever built at the
time.
A sprawling city with multiple areas.
Two huge pyramids overlook the center,
among which that of the Jaguar priest,
the ultimate symbol of power.
On this 12,000 square meter plaza, the
Royal Palace towered over the entire
valley.
Across from it, one of the greatest
necropolis in the Maya world was home to
the king's tombs.
Further west was Temple 4.
Standing at 70 m, it was the highest
temple ever built in Meso America.
Moreover, an ingenious hydraulic system
carried water across the entire city.
All of this brilliance was at the
service of the most powerful Maya
[music] kings, considered gods among
men.
This is where they flaunted their power
in front of hundreds of thousands of
people during massive ceremonies.
It would have been an amazing spectacle
and a great source of power. I mean they
had wars and so on but if you're a ruler
of one of their vassal [music] states
that's you know 100 150 km away [music]
you would come to this and you would
have the honor of being a participant.
The theater is the thing. It is not
reinforcing power. [music] It is a great
part of the power itself.
The kings exerted their power over a
plethora of Maya cities that were under
their rule.
And yet, in just a few decades, the
mighty Tikall would mysteriously sink
into oblivion.
Swallowed by the tropical forest, it
would take over a thousand years until
the first western expeditions of the
19th century rediscovered its splenders.
But the majestic city didn't immediately
give up all of its mysteries.
Some of its secrets are about to be
unraveled thanks to a revolutionary
tool.
Lidar.
It's a surveying method consisting of a
super powerful laser aboard a plane that
can see through the tree canopy and
reveal the slightest fluctuations in the
terrain.
>> Now lighter is our x-rays. We can see
the landscape. We can see every single
modification the Mayas did. Not the not
just only the major architecture
features. We also can see areas where
they were farming. They were almost
invisible for us.
>> Over 2,000 km of forest have been
scanned, allowing the discovery of
60,000 previously unseen human
structures.
Lidar has far exceeded expectations of
the archaeologists.
It reveals the city had a completely
different size, one much greater than
all previous projections.
We used to have [music] 16 square
kilometers. Now we have 75 square
kilometers and with the per urban area
is around 527
square kilometers is the size of what is
now Guatemala city and Guatemala city
can host at least between 3 to four
million of people.
This discovery gives rise to several new
questions.
How could a city 38 times bigger than
ancient Rome be built in such an
environment?
And above all, how did it all start?
Around 800 BC, a [laughter] first
community made its way to this steep
location overrun with vegetation.
>> Yet, it was there in the middle of the
jungle that these nomads chose to settle
down.
>> Where do they come from? That's a
puzzle. All the Maya territory was in
movement all the time.
It's like a soda water in in a cup. You
start to see a lot of bubbles. And that
where thing is happening here in the
lowlands that you start to have a lot of
communities that were moving around this
landscape hunting and start farm.
>> These first inhabitants were soon joined
by others that swelled the ranks.
What was a simple community
turned into [music] a village.
Tikal was born.
You're not supposed to [music] have
civilization in tropical forest. It's
very, very wet. The soils are very thin,
very thin in some places because
everything's [music] tied up in the
canopy. Uh there are a few navigable
rivers and they're on the edge because
the water [music] goes through the
limestone down there.
In this green desert where water
immediately infiltrates the [music]
ground. The survival of the young city
seemed uncertain.
The Maya people of Tikal were however
about to make a rare and previous
discovery that would forever change
their [music] destiny. There were
springs and you know the water from
springs are is virginal water. It's
pristine water. It's really very um like
sacred [music] or magical. Imagine
having a spring. Water is coming from
the earth that will give you u an extra
significance to the landscape.
A blessed land on which the inhabitants
of Tikal would erect a first temple.
The lost world pyramid
located in the southeast of the current
city. This pyramid was rebuilt on
several occasions.
>> When they build the first structures,
they want to build another larger. What
they do, they cover this one and they
start to make another one on the top.
It's like you're looking at onion when
you cut it and you see different layers.
The earliest layer will be here in the
bottom and that where they found over
here in 1980s. Then is one of the oldest
structure in Tika. This 30 m pyramid
actually conceals five other older ones.
The first was built in 600 BC. It was
only 3 m high and 24 m wide.
Despite its modest size, it became the
nerve center of the Tikall community.
From the top, priests used to observe a
spectacle orchestrated by the gods
themselves,
the heavenly vault and its myriad of
stars.
You have priests up there, uh, you know,
making notes, seeing things for hundreds
and hundreds of years. They're getting a
real idea about these stars. The
movements of the stars will tell you a
lot about the future. They also tell you
when maybe you need [music] to do some
rituals or sacrifice.
>> Being able to predict the future was the
key to the immense power reserved to the
local elite.
a power for which they acquired
knowledge about the cycles of Venus, the
moon, and the sun.
In Tikal, the king star would even
condition the construction of the city
center.
These buildings are the ones that make
the solar observatory and depends how
the sun moves in the sky and will start
over here and will continue moving and
that's how they can mark. That where you
need the three buildings and the sun
will rise behind them.
>> Sitting on top of the lost world
pyramid, the priests observe the motion
of the sun. In October, it indicated the
beginning of the dry season. In April,
the start of the rainy season.
That's how the perfect orientation of
the temples symbolized the winter and
summer [music] solstesses.
The Maya used this system to figure out
when to sew and when to harvest of all
ancient civilizations. They would become
the best [music] astronomers.
Wasn't astronomy. This was astrology.
They weren't trying to refine science or
something. And there really is this.
It's not just Meso America. All around
the world, Stonehenge or whatever it is,
uh this is something that people record.
But the Maya got such a good control of
it. That's part one of the reasons they
worship time. It was so regular and
impressive.
>> In the first centuries AD, Tika was one
of the most flourishing cities in all
the Maya lands.
But its fate was about to be shaken up
by an unprecedented event.
4th century AD.
Central Mexico. Teayotiwakan,
the largest Mesoamerican city ever
built.
It was the capital of a mysterious
civilization looking to stretch its
empire and [music] take possession of
the riches of faraway Maya territory.
Tikal was a city that was highly
cultivated. It was a very sophisticated
city and Tikal remained as a leading
power in the Mayaolands and was very
attractive for takanos.
January 378,
men traveled across the arid lands of
Mexico towards the pat.
They were Teayotakano soldiers equipped
with the best weapons of the time.
The event is narrated on a headstone
[music] in Tikal.
The text on Zilla 31 tells us that on in
378 uh at the same day when the
foreigners arrived the king of Tikal
died.
This is clearly not a peaceful arrival
of just [music] a few merchants. We are
talking about soldiers here and they
established a new dynasty.
Teayotiwakan seemed to have subjugated
Tical
but not everyone agrees.
I [music] tend to think that it may be a
bit exaggerated. I mean, you know, it's
not like now. It's like Napoleon said,
armies, you know, travel on their
stomach. There's a lot of people who
come along to help support. You better
show me, you know, commoners, uh,
pottery, the people that came with them.
And we don't have anything like that
yet.
While no archaeological evidence
confirms the invasion of Tikall by
Teayoti Wakan,
other elements have shown that the two
cities maintained commercial ties well
before 378.
Then what role did the Teati Wakanos
play in the Maya city?
Thanks to Liidar and for the [music]
first time ever in Tiko, archaeologists
are about to unravel its mystery.
light that is showing that the before
they thought there was a natural hill.
Now you can see the is very similar to
lassadela of tiwakan and that where we
think they maybe was a tootiwakan bario
some500 km [music] away the citadel is
one of the three major temples in
teotiwakan.
It's a gigantic structure comprising a
surrounding wall, a vast courtyard and a
temple.
Its shape is strangely similar to the
image detected by LAR.
A few hundred meters from the center of
Tikal in the midst of the tropical
forest. Initial excavations seem to
confirm the archaeologist hunch.
This is the eastern structure facing
west and is this is the area that we
think is very similar to Wakan.
But we want to prove these people they
have the knowledge of the otiwakan they
know the culture they know how to build
this structures they know the meaning of
that kind of architecture and that what
we are trying to to prove with this
excavation
>> pending the results of these excavations
other elements prove the influence of
the remote central Mexican capital
near the lost world pyramid is a temple
that has Teayoti Wakan written all over
it.
This is how we call it in Meso America
[music] architecture um talo. It's a
type of architecture that is very common
in Meso America
that you going to have a talude there is
this wall over here and a taboo that you
can see it here on the top. Now we only
can see the stones. But before like a
thousand years ago, these structures
were uh painted and covered with a
plaster. Most of the buildings here were
painted in red. And sometimes the
taberos were used also to depict some
[music] type of art.
>> Already widespread in Teayoti Wakan, the
Taloo Tablero technique became highly
popular in Tikal.
The people from the ancient Mayas they
knew about the symbolism of this type of
architecture and the elites of from here
tried to emulate those type of
architecture. There was a fashion but
also was a make the tie connections
between them and the elites of
now an ally of the most powerful city in
all of Meso America. Tikal became the
nerve center of Pen and extended its
influence all the way to Copan.
But the domination was short-lived. In
fact, two centuries later, when the
Teotiwakano Empire collapsed, a weakened
Tikall was conquered by a rival city,
Kalakmul,
located about 150 km to [music] the
north and led by the Khan dynasty.
Destitute of his prestige, would Tikal
ever rise from the ashes?
>> August 6th, [music] 695.
The faithful soldiers of Jasa Chan
Kawil, new king of Tikal savored their
revenge.
>> After 130 years of submission to
Kalakmool, they had just won a decisive
battle.
>> Humiliated, the survivors in the rival
army could only await their sacrificial
demise.
To mark his victory, Jasa Chan Kawil
ordered the construction [music] of two
gigantic temples.
They defeated the great enemy [music]
giant powerful hegemony of Kalakm.
And he [snorts] wanted to make a
statement. We're back. And so these
temples are very different. They do not
have temples inside of them. They were
not built. Most of the temples are like
Russian dolls. They were built all at
once. All of them, which is amazing.
The Temple of the Mask would comprise
four massive pedestals and [music] stand
42 m high.
Across [music] from it, the Temple of
the Jaguar Priest embodied Jasa Chan
Kawil's absolute power.
It would reach 47 m in height, becoming
one of the symbols of the city.
>> When you see this architecture and some
[music] of the other things the Maya
did, uh, you know, they say this must
have been space people. The way they
carve jade, it must be aliens [music] or
something. But, um, they had all these
clever techniques.
One of the techniques in which the
people of Tical became true experts was
the art of leveling.
[music]
Before building a pyramid, the Maya
would level the ground and cover it with
a thick platform.
One of the things that [music] people
don't realize about Tikall is that the
massive amount of labor that goes into
platforms.
This whole area looks [music] nice and
flat. It's an enormous platform.
But what is really impressive is that
the whole area of the site is a series
of platforms.
For the main plaza, the Maya built no
fewer than 12,000 m of platform.
It took about 16 km of it to level the
center of the city.
These platforms and pyramids, however,
required astronomical quantities of
material.
They also represented a considerable
technical challenge for a people that
didn't master metal work.
>> Luckily, the subs soils of Tikal were
packed with an easily accessible and
endless resource,
limestone.
The Maya exploited the limestone
different ways, not only for
construction materials for also for for
tools.
The core of the limestone, it's very
hard. So they created axes. Uh they
created hammers, they created spears.
They use these tools to extract the
millions of tons of stone needed for
their colossal construction sites.
So they trace, they design the trace of
the stone that they want to cut, but
also [music] they burn the limestone in
order to create plaster to cover all the
walls.
That is showing us the knowledge and
sophistication that the Maya achieved by
controlling and using this material.
The Maya had to carry the carved stone
on their backs as they didn't have
beasts of burden.
Yet, it took them less than two decades
to complete what would become the new
city center.
An enormous endeavor carried out by
thousands of workers.
this is something you do uh for the Holy
Lord and it [music] wasn't because they
were forced to do it. They had captive
but they didn't have a lot of slaves.
I don't think anybody was coerced. Um we
find that hard to believe but um again
they were devoutly religious
>> at top this new pyramid.
And away [music] from prying eyes, Jasa
Chan Kawil was about to perform a sacred
ritual.
A self-sacrifice during which he pierced
his own penis.
The ensuing blood was thought to have
predigious [music] virtues.
Blood is the absolutely central element
to all their thinking. That blood is
what connects to the ancestors and
[music] also the deities. And then he'll
see the vision serpent or have some
other hallucinations. [music] That's
what connects him to the future.
>> As he predicted the future to his
people, Jasach Chan Kaw became more than
a prophet.
>> He was the earthly envoy of the gods,
the key to holding infinite power.
This was the big highest ritual of the
Maya. This is when they would have
thousands of people, tens of thousands
of people coming in from everywhere. And
then the king would come out. And this
is what's really amazing, especially
here with these steep temples.
>> The temple of the Jaguar priest was
conceived following a very specific
design.
Each of the nine terraces represented
one of the nine levels of the
underworld, the kingdom of the dead.
At the center of the pyramid was the
axis mundi, the imaginary thread
connecting the underworld, the human
world, and the world of the gods.
In Maya hieroglyphic writing, the word
for temple is wid, which is the same
word as mountain. And many temples um
therefore embody uh ritual places or
places where the creation had taken
place. And kings could reenact
um events of the mythological past on
these temples.
But in the meantime, it was south of the
main plaza that Jasa [music] Chan Kawil
would reign over the world of the living
in a palace overlooking the entire
valley.
A series of constructions accommodated
the court, the clergy, the city
planners, and a cohort of servants.
Between 200 and 300 people lived around
[music] this inner courtyard, all in the
service of the king.
In that central room is a throne where
the king would sit and the visiting
people would come uh sometimes nobles
with a petition. Uh sometimes another
visiting ruler and this was a private
area for elites.
festivals in here where the nobles and
and rulers would they would often be
there'd be hallucenic uh enemas in one
side and the king is dancing, you know,
and there's some there's others dancing
with a snake and uh some of the nobles
looking up into the air and there's
floating porcupines wearing beads and uh
and an anoa pouch over in the side and
they were obviously taking [music]
hallucinagen
Initially three stories high and 215 m
long, the palace was a maze of long and
narrow rooms.
The rooms tend to be [music] narrow. Uh
because they did not have the true arch.
Um they had the corbold vault they call
it which the stones it's like a a child
[music] with blocks building. There's
stone and then another one closer,
another one closer, another one closer
and a [music] capstone. So it has it's
unstable as a tendency to collapse.
That's because the Maya didn't know
about the keystone.
Well known in the western world, that
technique allows to transfer the weight
of an arch to the retaining walls.
But since the Maya used corbell arches,
nothing allowed the forces to be
distributed.
this sort of long [music] narrow high uh
style that was really a result of you
know technology. They embraced it and so
they built their temples that way with
the roof combs and so on because there
would be wooden things to sit on with a
beautiful pillows and curtains and it
would have been a beautiful little room.
>> The year was now 7:34 AD.
It saw the death of Jasa Chan Kawil
after a reign of five decades that left
a profound imprint on the city.
His body was buried 6 m under the
pyramid of the Jaguar priest.
And it's a massive burial. It's a huge
burial chamber. One of the largest
burial chambers we know from the Maya
lands. And after the burial chamber, the
temple uh temple one, the temple of the
great jaguar was constructed over it.
Jasa Chan Kawil thus joined the pantheon
of the kings of Tiko.
Before that, about 20 of his
predecessors had been buried just a few
feet away in the north acropolis.
During a lavish ceremony, the deceased
was groomed for [music] his final
journey.
>> Luxurious offerings demonstrated his
[music] rank.
They buried their dead under the floors.
You wanted to be near your ancestors.
And [music] uh if someone was important,
they might turn that eventually into a
shrine [music] and it would become
bigger. And and here especially in
Tikal, one structure would then grow
into a temple. [music]
This is one of the great unique things
of Tikal that you have one place where
they are all buried. It's it's it's a
cemetery of kings.
>> About a hundred temples were built on
top of one another over the course of
centuries.
Some of them covered monumental
sculptures of Shak, the rain deity.
Tikk reasserted itself as the staple
city of the Paten.
His future king would have to defend
that status which aroused the envy of
the neighboring cities.
On December 8th, 734, the son of the
late king exceeded to the throne. His
name Yikin Chan Kawil.
Yikin Chan Kawil must have been a great
war leader. [music] He had ambitions to
to enlarge that the territory that was
controlled by Tikal [music] and um he
directed his military attacks against
former vessels of uh the Khan dynasty.
So what he did is he completed the work
which was begun by his father.
Yikin Chan Kawil sent his soldiers to
wipe out the last resisting bastions of
Khan faithful.
He thus consolidated the borders of this
empire.
But flooring his enemies wasn't enough.
>> It's just like Raison Silly in that the
battling was not just war.
It was who has the best rituals. Look
who had look at the temples. You know
who has the artists exactly like the
Renaissance.
To reinforce his power, Nikkin Chan
Kawil embarked on the construction of a
temple more ambitious still than his
fathers before him. Temple 4.
Now covered in jungle green, it peaks at
70 m.
It is the highest temple ever built in
Meso America.
The inclination is uh really really
steep. And the amazing thing [music] is
these steps they go down um like 200 m
and the king would genally bloodlet.
Imagine if you were had just lost lers
of blood and then [music] you would
process with 200 lb of equipment down
these stairs in a dignified way and uh
they had to train the princes probably
from the time they were five or six in
doing this and I know of no case that
that is recorded anywhere of a king
falling cuz you're dead if you fall. So
I it's just that is also imp. I wouldn't
want to be a Maya king by the way.
>> Temple 4 featured a dizzying [music]
slope of 82 degrees.
How did the Mayan design this pyramid
that remains intact some 1,300 years
later?
In order to understand, archaeologists
dug up a tunnel to the heart of the
pyramid.
Much to their surprise, they discovered
another structure inside.
>> We are right now in front of those
walls, we were thinking that that was an
earlier version of the temple. But once
we saw all the way on both sides and
different sides of the structure, we
come to the conclusion talking with the
masons. This was not an earlier version,
but a construction beans.
Some 250 cells, each 4 m in length and
1.6 m in height, were appended to one
another all the way to the top like a
giant beehive.
This structure supported [music] 119
cubic meters of backfill and prevented
the pyramid from collapsing under its
own weight.
>> [music]
>> architects artical are recognized to
have been one of the best in the May
area.
>> They knew they had to do something. I
mean, they were afraid it would fall
down. I I think Don't you think that
it's possible that just like in Egypt
there are somewhere around here earlier
experiments that failed and that's how
they learned to do this? Cuz you know in
Egypt the the collapse pyramid at Medum
and the Ben pyramid you know this is
steeper
>> and it didn't collapse.
>> So you can like make jokes to the
Egyptian archaeologists when you see
them about their sad little pyramids.
>> Yeah this is more a lot of stable right
and it is still in here.
>> In order to support the colossal weight
[music] of the pyramid the Maya had to
stabilize the ground.
To that end, they built a platform 5 m
in thickness and with a surface area of
15,000 [music] square meters.
A layer of stucco completed the
construction.
We are standing right now on a floor
that is about [music] 10 cm thick. Can
you imagine the amount of wood burn that
amount of limestone in order to just to
get this floor done? That was a huge
effort. And this uh platform is on top
of the bedrock. So, it couldn't be more
solid.
>> It would take the Maya workers less than
10 years to build temple 4.
An absolute feat.
>> That's very fast. You know, because the
Egyptian pyramids, they would sometimes
[music] build it just when the next
pharaoh was born. They would start
building it. It took so long.
>> Yeah. It's incredible how the ruler was
concentrated with such an amount of
people and resources and how sure he was
that he was going to make it. And then
once you began that is not something
okay I'm gonna leave it just like that
in the middle or a third or oneird or
two/3 you once you are on the on the
enterprise you need to finish it [music]
and he made it.
The construction of temple 4 marked the
apex of the city.
Based on the latest estimates its
population [music] then reached 60,000
people.
This required enormous water and food
resources.
If you really want to have these [music]
huge cities, you have to make sure that
there's water available for everybody
and you don't have to walk 5 kilometers
to bring a jar of water. [music]
>> It was obvious that the city couldn't
solely rely on its single source of
water.
The Maya hence had a brilliant idea.
Using the inclination of the squares to
collect precious rainwater,
this park was open to the public. They
hired an Italian company whose specialty
was hydraulic [music] systems because
they wanted to make sure that when it
rains, water won't interfere with the
visit. And we were impressed to see that
the set of canals these Italians put in
the in the park are exactly on top of
the hydraulic system that the Maya chose
more than 1500 years before.
>> The water collected was transferred to a
reservoir.
Crates filled with sand were used to
filter the water and make it drinkable.
When we find out, we were very excited
because we have no other reference like
that. [music] We have no other mention
of any other reservoir that has this
upper tank filled in with another
sediment different from the [music]
local material that it's very very very
likely it was used as filter.
>> The water was then transferred further
down in gigantic terrace tanks with a
capacity totaling 900,000 cub m.
To control the flow, two huge dams were
built
80 m wide and 10 m high. They were
carved out of the rock and ended with a
wall
blocked with wood or stone panels. The
pipes 30 cm in diameter allowed to check
water quality in each basin.
This complex system required a
significant workforce.
state will be in charge to keep them
working [music] to keep them clean.
Therefore, if they do that, they will
have the control to tell who can go to
these reservoirs, how much water can you
take and all that and they will make
sure that water flows through the
canals. So, but that's an assumption. We
think that's the way it work.
>> The Maya were able to take advantage of
a hostile forest and steep terrain.
pre-Colombian cultures. They were the
first landscapers. And if you look at
all the maps of the Maya cities, they
have like a like a very good order in
organization and in the settlement
pattern space they are using.
>> It was this ability to adapt that
allowed the Maya to farm enough to feed
the tens of thousands of locals.
Corn, beans, and wheat highlighted the
richness of the city, which continued to
attract new migrants daily.
With 80 to 120 inhabitants per square
kilometer, equal to the current
population density in a country like
France, [music]
it was one of the densest cities in the
world at the time.
How long would Tikal sustain its
exponential growth?
By the middle of the 8th century, the
city had vanquished all of its enemies.
It dominated an enormous territory
stretching from Kalakmool to Nanho.
Yet it struggled to manage such an
imposing area.
>> There was a vacuum of power and many
local [music] lords and local dynasties
uh started to proclaim themselves as
independent kings.
>> They say I am the divine lord of Tikal
and all of a sudden we have five or 10
divine lords of Tikal. For me this is a
beginning of the end.
>> Politically weakened Tikall would have
to deal with a new challenge.
an unprecedented drought.
>> Over the next century, precipitations
decreased by about 50%.
You know, they build these great
reservoirs. They build these great
roads. Then you have a period of drought
or decline or something and you're
dependent on them now and you can't
maintain them. And so it actually makes
it worse uh because now you have this
wonderful system and you can't maintain
it because and so then it spirals faster
down.
Faced with this climate issue, the elite
chose to build even more so as to
appease the anger of the gods and
encourage rain to return.
This reproachable behavior came with a
heavy price on the environment.
cities grew very big. They were really
abusing the landscape, like cutting too
many trees. If you see, for example, the
post holes of the pre-classic, there are
these big trees and then in the classic,
they were a little bit narrower and
narrower because they didn't let them
grow as big as before.
>> But again, this was really like
Versailles. It was incredibly
impressive, huge expenditure of energy
and setting the stage, you know, for the
for the revolution. In this case, there
is malnutrition. There are growing
ecological problems and they're sort of
just intensifying what they did before.
So, you know, again, it's a beautiful
disaster going on. I mean, the temples
are impressive and this sculpture and
that sculpture, but that really doesn't
help the economic system.
>> The city became an ogre that consumed
everything in its path.
Little by little, the people of Tikal
lost faith in their leaders who
multiplied the ceremonies hoping to stay
in power.
[screaming]
>> There's a big increment in a massive
sacrifices in more quantities than
before. So that can allow us to make an
interpretation that there's a a time of
crisis. [music]
The role of the elites is to keep this
status cool. And then the elites are not
able to hold the [music] status cool.
They're going to say, "Uh-uh, this
doesn't work. And I'm not going to pay
tribute because first I'm going to feed
my family and if the pyramid collapse,
whatever."
>> Faced with a shortage of water and the
helplessness of the elite, the
inhabitants [music] started to leave the
city. Cornered from all angles, Tikal
withdrew into itself. [music]
Thanks to their use of LAR in the
jungle, archaeologists have discovered
the traces of the city in dire straits.
This is the area where we found [music]
the new part of this defensive wall of
Tikal and that's where we're going to be
interesting to go and check. And you see
here lighter stop right here. and what
happening over what is happening over
here. That where we're going to see when
we extend our lighter map to try to
understand if it surrounded the entire
area or not. But that we're going to do
it in with the new lighter map.
>> A 6 m tall outer wall seemed to have
surrounded the city.
But for what purpose? What were the
elite of Tikall fearing?
It's not just for protecting in during a
war also is it's trying [music] to make
people to don't move like also you can
stop some type of migrations. We know
the Mayas migrate a lot when a city
collapse or something people will moving
and I think also it's controlling
[music] people. We still don't know who
can was able to go and cross and get to
another city. Everybody could do it or
every can go and farm in different
cities. We don't know that yet.
The elite seemingly tried to contain the
bleeding, but in vain.
The gods remained deaf to their appeals.
Rain didn't come.
In less than a century, Tikall became a
ghost town.
Throughout the Paten, the cities fell
one after the other.
>> It's the network. A civilization is a
network of all these and it had
collapsed and so the fact that this site
or that site stumbled on Tikall
continued for a while in a pathetic way
but many of the places I mean many sites
it was boom it was pretty fast [music]
however it's a thermostat you know the
the heat builds up builds up builds up
and then boom the air conditioning goes
on and so sudden but these things
throughout the lake class. They were
built.
And that's how Tikall collapsed after
being one of the greatest and most
glorious Maya cities of all time.
A gigantic city with vast unexplored
sections that Liidar is finally
revealing.
Under the thick jungle, the city state
isn't done revealing its secrets.
Who knows what revelations Tikall
[music] still holds about this
astounding civilization of builders.
some [music] 45 km from Mexico lies the
birthplace of the gods Teayotiwakan.
Erected in the 1st century AD, it was as
heavily populated as Athens.
Its 65 m pyramid of the sun is the
second largest in the world after the
Great Pyramid of Giza. built using only
man's muscle power.
>> All of Tiwakan was created without any
metal which is amazing because that
[music] includes everything from the
construction equipment. So it wasn't the
technology, it was the people that
created Tetiwakan.
>> Of all Mesamerican cities, Teayotiwakan
is the most mysterious.
>> It was the stage of thousands of human
sacrifices.
Its unique construction is the work of
builders who [music] identity remains
unknown.
They [music] were like Martians. I mean
they pulled in people into this highly
organized city on a grid system. This
was like nothing before.
an enigma, the key of which may lie
deeply buried in a 102 m long tunnel
beneath the pyramid of the feathered
serpent.
>> My theory is that for a period of time,
the end of the tunnel was used to store
the remains of someone specific, someone
with a lot of power, most likely a first
era leader of Teot Wakan.
Archaeologists have recently made local
discoveries that reveal the secrets
behind the construction of history's
very first pre-Colombian [music]
megalopouloolis.
[music]
Heat. Heat.
Teati Wakan,
a city born out of an incredibly crazy
idea.
To build the city as a giant cosmogram,
a perfect replica of the universe, as a
way to reach the level of the gods.
Following a perfectly orthogonal layout,
the city is divided into four quadrants
separated by two avenues oriented by the
four cardinal points.
At their intersection, the temple of the
feathered serpent dedicated to the snake
god Quzawat symbolizes the center of the
universe.
At the north end of the 2 km long avenue
of the dead is the pyramid of the moon.
[music] Standing 42 m high and perfectly
aligned with Sra Gordo Peak.
Facing west, the 215 m wide pyramid of
the sun is only rivaled by the Great
Pyramid of Giza in Egypt.
The surrounding lands feature 2,200
dwellings [music] spreading over 23
square kilm.
A gigantic city that reached 200,000
inhabitants in its heyday and which took
5 centuries to complete.
>> Wakan was an impressive city, one of the
five largest cities in the whole world
back then.
>> It's really not just the city, it's a
landscape. It's so massive that the
imprint of the ancient city still is
making thousands and millions of people
from all over the world come to visit
it. That's how successful they were as
far as creating a convincing uh template
that attracted that number of people.
The city became a hot spot for
worshippers thanks to its many lavish
ceremonies. Much like on this night in
350 AD
from the Avenue of the Dead, tens of
thousands of pilgrims marched toward the
pyramid of the moon.
At its peak and with their hands tied,
men awaited in fear.
coming from all four corners of Central
America. They were diplomats, warriors,
or merchants.
All well-born individuals whose
sacrifice was expected to please the
gods and consecrate the imposing [music]
monument.
With a swoop of the razor sharp obsidian
axe, the men were beheaded.
They all suffered the same fate and
their corpses were placed in the heart
of the great pyramid.
>> Every culture in the world practiced
sacrifices. Even the Romans and the
Greeks. They all practiced human
sacrifice. But it was something very
special here. It was deeply rooted in
daily life. Whether as self-sacrifice,
collective or familial sacrifice or even
entire neighborhoods. You don't select
just anyone for sacrifice. They have to
be specific individuals selected for
becoming the ultimate sacrificial
victims representing the state that are
able to uh fulfill the function of a
successful ritual dedication.
For what reason? Well, it was a way to
guarantee the durability of their
landmarks. And when they wanted to build
a new monument, they had to carry out a
new sacrifice. The more they gave, the
more they expected to receive.
>> While it is the most impressive,
Teayotwakan is also the most mysterious
city of Meso America. Its civilization
left no trace behind, and its true name
fell into complete oblivion.
It was only centuries after its fall
that the Aztecs, standing before such
perfection, gave the city the name of
Teayoti Wakan, meaning birthplace of the
gods.
One question has continued to plague
archaeologists ever since.
Who built this most incredible
pre-Colombian city?
In the 1st century BC, at an altitude of
2,275
m, men and women from northern Mexico
crossed the semi-erid highlands in
search of a place to settle.
a journey that would lead them all the
way to the valley of Mexico.
>> I believe that there were people back
then who were geommancers.
>> Geommancy is a little known gift. Those
who have it are able to determine where
a city should be founded.
>> And they [music] moved into the the
valley of Mexico, which is a rich rich
valley. And [music] because of the the
richness of the soils and so on, they
were able to pull people together
physically and still support them.
An abundance that would draw an
everinccreasing number of migrants to
Teayot Wakan in just a few decades.
There were between 15 and 20,000
inhabitants,
which was already a large colony for
that time,
and those men and women needed to be
fed.
So, they obviously had to figure out a
way to increase the yield of their
crops.
A soaring population that pushed city
leaders to rethink traditional
agricultural practices.
A food shortage would [music] have
clearly been fatal to the young city.
To increase food production, they
[music] came up with an ingenious system
of irrigation.
Fed by rainwater, two reservoirs,
[music]
each 500 m long, 5.5 m wide, and 1.4 m
deep, irrigated large expanses of
agricultural [music] land.
The water was pulled by gravity into
grooves [music] carved into the bedrock,
which maintained constant humidity in
the thin layer of arable [music] soil.
A complex system that allowed for
multiple harvests annually, much to the
prestige of the city's elite.
[music]
>> It's highly likely that the group that
oversaw the planning and construction of
the system started to gain more and more
power. The political authority of
Tetivakan is very well contested, right?
Some people say that it was a type of
[music] collaborative rulership and some
say no, it was a very traditional
autocratic rulership which one ruler
that ruled resided over the city itself.
The reason we're contesting it so much
is [music] because one, we don't have a
writing system. So we don't have a
history of you know the Maya area they
have lavishly engraved epigraphic
records of every ruler every affair he
had. We don't have that at Tetiwakan.
The second thing is that we don't
actually have a burial of a king. So a
centralized authority it [music] doesn't
have to be one person but it's much
easier if it is. So until I see evidence
for the [music] contrary, I think it's
really important to keep that in mind.
>> Whether or not they shared their power,
the city's elites definitely had some
serious competition in the region.
The south was home to the Zapotech
Empire and the impressive city of Monte
Albban. To the east was the powerful
Maya [music] civilization and its
monumental cities of Nagb and Kalakmul.
And just a day away on foot to the
southwest was Kuwilko, the largest urban
center in the valley of Mexico at the
time.
And all of these cities were home to
monumental pyramids.
Religion played a fundamental role in
the creation of the world for the
ancient people of Meso America. There's
not a single city that wasn't built
around a temple.
It was a central cohesive element.
>> Pyramids are really artificial
mountains. They are able to bring to
life. You know, it's not just a
mountain, but it's the mountain where
the ancestor spirits are living. That's
how you communicate with your ancestors.
It's about being able to connect [music]
with the community and the gods and the
whole ecological order by building these
[music] mountains.
>> Teayoti Wakan didn't simply want to
rival [music] its powerful neighbors. It
wanted to dominate them.
To that end, builders needed to devise a
city unlike any other and make Teayoti
Wakan the beacon of a new era.
The year was 50 AD.
The future city began to take shape
[music] around an immense road that was
2 km long and 70 m wide. The avenue of
the dead.
This central [music] access then
branched into a network of perfectly
perpendicular streets and alleyways.
A city grid that foreshadowed large
modern metropolises like New York City
or Beijing.
It was urban planning on an
unprecedented level anywhere in the
world.
That's why we consider Teayoti Wakan to
be the most perfect example of urban
planning.
They were like Martians. I mean they
pulled in people into this highly
organized city on a grid system. This
was like nothing before. that would have
required [music] um something like that
to be impressive to make a statement.
A statement of power.
A statement of power illustrated by
three sanctuaries.
The first at a colossal 65 m high and
215 m wide was the pyramid of the sun.
With a volume of over 1 million cubic
meters, it's the biggest pyramid ever
built [music] in Meso America.
>> This pyramid was the megaphone of
Teotiwakan. This is what everybody
looked towards. No matter if you're a
farmer in the hinterlands of Teotiwakan,
[music]
you saw the pyramid. You saw what was
going on. You saw the smoke signal. It
doesn't matter where you live. You will
>> [music]
>> identify with the Sun Pyramid. You will
be proud to be part of this city so
magnificent that [music] it radiates its
presence throughout the whole valley.
>> A pyramid dedicated to the most sacred
star of Meso America, the sun.
The structure was precisely oriented
15.5°
east of astronomical north.
The western wall is perfectly aligned
with the setting sun on August 12th,
which marks the beginning of the dry
season. And on April 29th, which marks
the beginning of the rainy season,
>> they were sky watchers. They were
scientists and astrologers that
interpreted the sun, predicted eclipses,
understood the Venus cycle. Um, and so
it's really incredible to understand how
meaningful
this place was,
>> the exact, you know, movement of the
stars and making [music] their time
system and so on was astrology. And, you
know, in some of these, uh, people say,
well, they could predict the seasons and
when to plant. That's quite [music]
ridiculous. Um, I mean the farmers knew
about this a lot better than the kings.
And so these [music] things had a
religious meaning.
>> A pyramid connected to the stars but
also used to keep time.
That's because the teati wakanos
designed the building according to
ancient Mesoamerican calendars.
The Hob comprised of 365 [music] days
symbolizing the solar cycle
and the Sulken, a ritual calendar of 260
days divided into 13 months of 20 days
[music] each.
A complex calendar system which thanks
[music] to a recent discovery has also
been tied to the unit of measurement
used by Teati Wakano Architects, the
TMU.
a standard length of [music] 83 cm
corresponding roughly to the distance
between a human's fingertips and their
heart.
What's fascinating about this
measurement unit is that they actually
tell us a little bit about how they were
able to materialize what they saw into
the sky and how they interpret that
physically into the walls, the rooms.
Therefore, the 215 m width of the
pyramid of the sun corresponds to 260
tmus, the exact number of days on the
ritual calendar.
The pyramid was surrounded by a 34 m
wide platform bringing its depth to 431
m or 520 Teot Wakan measurement units,
twice the symbolic number of 260.
When I say the Tetuakanos were ingenious
engineers, I'm not kidding. [music] You
know, they really were able to not only
kind of make it look nice, it actually
really made you embody the cosmos by
just walking through the city itself.
That's [music] what a better way to
experience Tiwakan than embodying their
understanding of the whole world works
through experience.
But beyond symbolism, the architects
needed to figure out how to erect such a
massive monument.
To do so, they relied on an unexpected
ally.
Boboka,
a volcano located 100 km to the south of
Teayotiwakan,
which had been forming the foundation of
the Valley of Mexico for thousands of
years.
An almost inexhaustible supply of
volcanic rock [music] was extracted by
workers from dozens of underground
quaries all around the city.
They call [music] it specifically this
type of basalt which is locally called
tessontle. And this tesson has a lot of
pores. So it's very lightweight and you
can shape it very easily. So it's easier
to carry to you want to build buildings.
That's why they preferred uh these this
type of rocks. But they were not
available on the surface. They had to
dig below the teeter layer. This is
volcanic tough and this is very uh soft
as you see here.
You can destroy it very easily. And they
crashed teet to make a base of the
floor.
In total, some 715,000
cubic meters of this rock was extracted
from the earth to build the entire city
of Teotiwakan.
The material was then carried by men on
their backs for hundreds of meters.
That's because pre-Colombian
civilizations never domesticated animals
to help them carry heavy loads.
They compensated for the lack of pack
animals with an efficient use of
manpower.
The people were the labor force and they
were very effectively put to work in a
well organized way in order to be
productive. That's one of the
characteristics of Mesoamerican
societies.
The rulers of the city knew they had an
abundant supply of workers.
The population of Teoti Wakan and its
surroundings was already at 80,000
inhabitants.
Men from each family were selected to be
part of [music] the workforce.
Religion played a very important role in
controlling the people and the
workforce.
That's something that had never been
seen before. It's very different from
slavery, capitalism, or feudalism. Here,
you could own tools and land, but they
controlled the power of your labor.
During the dry season, tens of thousands
of builders worked tirelessly on the
enormous construction of the pyramid.
Such a massive structure could have very
well crumbled beneath [music] its own
weight.
To prevent that from happening, a
mound-shaped wall was built around the
pyramid.
The interior of the structure was
supported with a grid of cells made of
adobe bricks, a mix of straw and clay.
The holes were then filled with dirt and
rocks,
a process that was [music] repeated
layer after layer all the way to the
top.
This honeycomb structure allowed the
building to withstand the heavy weight
of the filling within the pyramid.
Construction cells, they were not
invented [music] at Tuaka, but in
Pueblo. And the reason why that
technique was developed or invented is
unknown but I suspect that around 50 to
70 there was a huge vol or volcanic
eruption of popocate and I assume there
was huge earthquake
and it is possible that many structures
were destroyed. Then those people
possibly experimented using different
techniques and then finally invented the
technique of construction cells. [music]
So to keep those pyramids stable, taken
people emulated or imitated those
techniques.
The pyramid of the sun is the mightiest
structure ever built by manpower alone.
How long did it take the Teayoti Wakano
people to build it?
No one really knows.
Although many archaeologists share
similar beliefs about the answer, a
recent experiment has shed new light on
the conversation.
The construction of a miniature temple
using the same tools and materials from
back then.
We completed the whole process in two
weeks with four workers. And the most
intriguing thing I learned through this
process is that we try to keep the walls
uh flat but actually we failed. It was
not possible for us. I still do not
understand how to people [music] did it
especially for large buildings. So based
on our experiments, I calculated the
time necessary to complete the sun
pyramid. And I think it took less than
10 years and possibly around 6 years,
which is much less time than previously
thought.
An achievement that continues to impress
[music] and puzzle archaeologists some
2,000 years later.
How could the same people who built such
structures disappear without leaving
behind any clues about their identity?
South of the avenue of the dead, beneath
the pyramid of the feathered serpent, is
the second main sanctuary in Teotiwakan.
15 meters below the surface, a
mysterious tunnel that was discovered
[music] in 2003 could unravel the
mystery.
Entirely carved out with rudimentary
tools, this man-made cavity is covered
in a thin layer of mud and follows an
east to west orientation.
The tunnel stretches over 102 m.
15 m from the entrance, a series of 23
walls, each 1 m thick, were built to
block access into the tunnel. The tunnel
was sealed three separate times with
walls that go from the floor to the
ceiling.
Then they would destroy the walls to get
inside again, but we don't know for what
purpose. And then they'd rebuild new
walls on top of the remains of the old
walls. Later they came back, but for
some reason they left without rebuilding
the walls. Instead, they filled the
tunnel with lots of dirt and rocks.
My theory is that for a period of time,
the end of the tunnel was used to store
the remains of someone specific, someone
with a lot of power, most likely a first
era leader of Teotu Wakan.
[music]
Could this tunnel have been the tomb of
the Teatiwakan kings?
For the first time, archaeologists seem
to be close to solving the puzzle.
At the end of the first section, which
is 65 m long, the narrow tunnel suddenly
drops.
>> The majority of the tunnel's first
section was dug about 15 m below the
surface. And this here is deeper. It
goes down to 17 m. I think this whole
section must have been how they accessed
what we believe to be the most sacred
and important spot of the entire tunnel.
I believe it's the gateway to the real
world, the truth, and the real
underworld.
An intriguing sparkle in the rock
attracts the eye. [music]
A phenomenon that's far from natural.
The entire tunnel must have been covered
with this sparkling mineral powder. It's
made of three minerals, pyite, hematite,
and magnetite, which were brought here
from far away and painted on these
walls, the ceiling, and even the floor
of the tunnel. It must have been an
extremely important religious experience
to enter here in total darkness with
only the light from your torch. As the
flame flickered, it must have looked
like the sky and the stars of the
underworld.
At the end of the tunnel, three chambers
facing east, south, and north form a
cross,
the center of which is perfectly aligned
with the peak of the pyramid.
This imaginary vertical axis is called
the axis mundi.
There's a symbolic conduit here that
connects all three levels of the cosmos.
The entire world rotates around this
vertical axis. What continues to amaze
us is how the teotanos this deep were
able to precisely calculate how to
perfectly align this point with the
summit of the pyramid of the feathered
serpent.
Although no tomb was [music] discovered
here, archaeologists did make another
incredible discovery.
Four stone statues representing three
women and a man, all facing the axis
[music] mundi.
We discovered the remains of another
sculpture much larger than the four
others.
It appears to have been a male figure.
It was naked like the others, but all we
found at this spot was a foot and 100 m
further a leg. We believe that means
that when the Teod Aanos came into this
place, likely to desacize the tomb of
the man who was buried here. They also
destroyed the sculpture, which likely
represented him. From what we know, the
Teot Waganos were iconoclastic. They
destroyed the symbols of power
associated with a person at the time of
their death.
>> Sacred rituals [music] must have been
carried out here.
Rituals like this king's ceremonial
burial.
A man whose influence spanned far beyond
the city's borders.
>> When the funeral ceremony took place,
The entire Mesoamerican world sent
gifts,
presents to accompany the dead king that
was buried here. It must have been a
very important event that affected the
entire Mesoamerican world.
Although the name of this king has
forever been forgotten, the tens of
thousands of offerings left in the
tunnel could provide important insights
into the Teayotiwakan civilization.
>> [music]
>> They include objects made of jade or
amber
as well as finely carved shells, many of
which share something in common. They're
all from Maya civilization.
There is nothing specific to Teotakan
here. Everything is 100% Maya. We've
been able to decode them thanks to
similar artifacts found on Maya sites
that are much older than Teoduan.
This glyph is very important. It means a
and a means king.
It's most likely connected to the
structure of power in Teodakan.
That's why I think that the Mayas
greatly contributed to the creation of
the ideology, the magical thinking and
the religious identity of Teot Wakan.
The Teotu Wakanos didn't create any
myths. They just borrowed the myths of
the ancient Mayas and then they
presented themselves as the creators and
the masters of the world. But in
reality, all the origins of this is
Maya.
The Mayas,
>> a people long considered to be
pacifistic, but who also practiced human
sacrifice.
Was the Teayoti Wakano's insatiable
thirst for blood inspired by the Mayas?
>> [screaming]
>> One thing is certain, this pyramid, the
last structure that completed the
historical heart of the city, saw more
bloody ceremonies than any other
edifice.
Located at the far north of the Avenue
of the Dead,
surrounded by 14 other pyramid
structures, lies the city's third key
religious sanctuary, the Pyramid of the
Moon. 46 m high, 149 m wide, and 168 m
deep, [music] it is built on multiple
levels connected by monumental
staircases.
It has been heavily explored since the
first Central American expeditions and
345 m of tunnels [music] have been dug
here in hopes of unraveling its secrets.
The excavations revealed incredible
discoveries.
The Moon Pyramid was constructed over a
sequence of time. So imagine an onion.
started off as a small dirt mound and
then they built over and over until it
become larger and larger. And so we know
from doing tunnel excavations at the
core of the pyramid that there were
seven building phases.
>> The first pyramid which is only 23 m
wide was designed to support the second
and the second supported the third. This
system allowed [music] to limit the
amount of backfill needed for each step.
In total, seven pyramids were built over
three centuries at [music] the northern
limit of the Avenue of the Dead.
>> One of the most important kind of
dimensions [music] of the city was the
front of the moon pyramid itself. It
always had to start from that point
because this point to, for example, the
end of the Avenue of the Dead was a
certain number of measurement units. And
so that's why they decided that they
always have to have the pyramid [music]
start from this section.
The Avenue of the Dead [music] is 2,156
m in length, which corresponds to 2,600
Teotiwakan measurement units, meaning 10
times the [music] number of days on the
ritual calendar.
Striving to preserve the exact length of
the Avenue of the Dead, the Teati
Wakanos gave the Pyramid of the Moon a
very particular shape. Originally it was
our kind of mound that grew three times.
When they build uh the fourth
construction pyramid, it becomes much
larger. It becomes what we know as a
monumental scale. Right? So when they
decided to add an adosada structure,
that's a next platform on top of the the
main body of the pyramid. They decide to
cut the edges [music]
of the smaller mound and then build
another main pyramid behind it because
that front had to be maintained. So
they're building over from the front
into [music] the back.
>> An important religious symbol, the
pyramid of the moon was key to the
strategy adopted by the leaders of
Teatiwakan
to make this city the most popular site
of pilgrimage in Meso America.
>> You could consider Teayoti Wakan the
great mecca of Meso America. [laughter]
That's why we think this large street,
the Avenue of the Dead, which is over 70
m wide, was designed to receive
thousands of people from all over
Central America.
>> You could imagine that on certain
occasions you would have parades where
people will be looking onto the avenue,
all of the people walking into the
dedicatory space, [music] the con
shells, you could hear them in the
background, but also the screeches and
the roars of the pumas and the eagles.
And this would [music] blow them away. I
mean, all those things painted now. And
they would go back and be impressed and
take some, you know, Teayoti Wakan
[music] uh influences with them.
These pilgrims spread the word of
Teotiwakan's grandeur across all of Meso
America.
>> [cheering]
>> Thousands of them journeyed here to
partake in lavish ceremonies that marked
the start and end of each phase in the
construction of the pyramid of the moon.
Rituals during which jaguars, pumas,
eagles, or even humans were sacrificed.
The great priest would finish off his
victims by ripping out their hearts.
The corpses were then buried in one of
six burial chambers within the pyramid's
filling, all precisely aligned along a
north south axis.
The way that they are arranged within
the dedicatory space is very important.
Both its orientation but also the
quantity. Certain numbers keep
reappearing. uh for example certain
calendarric numbers like the number of
days months of years the number 18 comes
up uh significantly it's the number of
golden eagles that were sacrificed in
burial six half of this number nine were
sacrificed in burial 2 I think so far
everything about tiwakan is intentional
it's just uh incredible to think about
how they were able to conceive of such a
master [music] plan and not only think
about it but execute it.
>> It was these three sanctuaries that made
Teati Wakan the most important [music]
religious center in all of Meso America.
And yet, barely two centuries after its
rise, the city underwent a new
revolution.
In 200 AD, Teayoti Wakan counted over
150,000 inhabitants, making it the most
populated city in Meso America.
On either side of the Avenue of the Dead
and its lavish temples, entire
neighborhoods sprang from the earth.
These residential complexes, much like
the Great Pyramids, were subject to very
strict rules of construction.
The entire city was built around the
cosmo vision of Teotakan,
the four cardinal points, north, east,
west, south, and also in relation to the
sun's position on certain dates.
The first city was oriented 11° east of
the magnetic north.
And when I say city, I don't mean only
the main road. the Avenue of the Dead
and its temples.
I also mean all of the structures, all
of the walls, the entire city.
Tens of thousands of dwellings that the
new king wanted to tear down as the
ruler wanted to impose a radical change
to the city's interpretation of
cosmogyny.
Reorient the city 15.5° east of magnetic
north.
A change that would lead [music] to a
large part of the city being destroyed
and rebuilt to fit the new layout.
>> It was insane. As insane as destroying
Paris, Rome, or New York City simply to
reposition everything by 3°, which isn't
even noticeable.
>> This is a tremendous amount of planning,
engineering, and infrastructure [music]
to get it right. remember they didn't
have the total stations we have today to
make sure that alignment is completely
[music] accurate and the people residing
in these locations didn't just squat
down. And [music] so it's amazing to
think about as far as what it took to
convince the already settled people to
reorient because [music] it's not just
reorienting a building. It's reorienting
the way that you walk, the way that you
have access in and out to the city
center and in, right? Getting your way
to the marketplace. It orients your
daily life in a very fundamental way.
[music]
>> How could one king, as powerful as he
may have been, impose such a radical
change upon his people?
The answer lies perhaps within the
structure of the living quarters itself,
an iconic part of the city. Surrounded
by a [music] perimeter wall that limited
access, each complex included living
spaces, storehouses, workshops, and most
importantly, a courtyard with an altar.
A central element [music] controlled by
the priests where domestic religion was
practiced.
The priests controlled the production of
all objects made in this space.
They distributed the raw materials
and collected many of the finished
products which then they offered to the
city's elites.
The weight of the local religion was
felt on every level.
It was everywhere. [music]
Whether you were at home or in the
biggest temples,
it was one of the ways that the elite
controlled the broader population.
Like the great [music] pyramids, the
entire city was painted in red pigment
extracted from a stone, hematite.
In the luxury dwellings reserved for the
elite,
walls were decorated with ornate fresco
of scenes strictly controlled by the
state.
>> The principal theme was this mountain.
It's an illusion to the [music]
god of the rain, the most important god
in tewan.
For example, in this part, we see what
appears to be a depiction of a
sacrifice.
There are also decapitated heads.
[snorts]
It's obvious that this is more than a
simple decorative painting. It is also a
clear representation of the Teatuano
Cosmo vision.
One of the ways they control the people
was by conveying the state's messages in
stone.
2200 living quarters spread across 23
square kilometers and overtook land that
had once been used for farming.
To continue to grow their city, the
leaders of Teotiwakan made what could be
considered a surprising decision.
Around 150 AD, they closed all of the
hydraulics, which required great effort,
and they stopped cultivating their own
food. [music]
Why would Teot Wakan stop its own food
production?
The Teot Lakhan Valley is actually very
small. So even if they had dedicated all
the available land to agriculture, that
still wouldn't have been enough to feed
a population greater than 30,000 people.
But there were 200,000 men and women
living in Teotu Wakan, which means that
most of the food consumed in the city
was imported.
a dependence that could become the
city's Achilles heel.
The Teatiwakanos made a very risky bet
and decided to make the city the largest
[music] artisinal production center in
Meso America.
To that end, they shifted their focus to
a strategic resource that was widely
available in the valley,
obsidian.
A volcanic rock with exceptional
physical properties.
>> Obsidian is a volcanic rock with very
sharp edges. It was the only material
they could use to make blades for
sacrifices or weapons. We believe there
were numerous workshops in the city that
were dedicated to making objects out of
obsidian. We know that obsidian played
an extremely important role in the
city's economy. And we found obsidian
artifacts in other places far away from
Teodwakan.
>> Now the greatest economic power in Meso
America, Teayot Tiwakan attracted
traders from all over Central America.
Entire neighborhoods of foreigners began
to spring [music] up.
The Zapotech neighborhood located 3 km
west of the Avenue of the Dead was
specialized in the production of
Stuckco. In the northwest, there was a
neighborhood that regrouped people from
the Veraracruz region and the Maya
lowlands.
Today, Teotu Vakan would have been a
multithnic city like New York City or
Paris where people from all over the
world dress and speak in a variety of
ways.
It seemed like nothing could stop the
incredible growth of the city.
A regional power up [music] until then,
Teayoti Wakan was about to take a new
step in its quest for domination.
The year was 200 AD.
In the valley of Mexico, Tadlan Klea and
Quil Kilko, [music]
Teayotiwakan's biggest competitors,
started to crumble. No one really knows
why.
And yet, at the same time, [music]
construction on a new pyramid in Teayoti
Wakan seemed to mark the end of a battle
of which the city emerged victorious.
When the construction of the pyramid of
the feathered serpent was set to begin,
a massive sacrifice of 260 people took
place. It's possible that they were
prisoners of war or rival leaders who
were brought here and sacrificed. They
were placed at the base of the
structure, hands tied behind their
backs. [music] They were all taller than
average. They all had weapons and were
adorned with warrior symbols.
Did this mass sacrifice signify [music]
a change in the Teoti Wakan power
structure?
Built directly above the old tunnel,
this new pyramid was dedicated to Quzac
Quatal, [music] the powerful feathered
serpent.
>> The feathered serpent brings this emblem
of time and the creation of new time on
its back. And the way that this was
materialized is by embedding a whole
military army within the nucleus of this
structure where this feathered serpent
is meandering on its frontal facade.
Right? So it's a very powerful message
that reflects the arrival of new
rulership.
A new sovereign had thus taken control
of the city.
an authoritarian leader whose goal was
[music] to make Teayoti Wakan the first
empire of Meso America.
The new pyramid was meant to surpass
[music] everything that had been
previously built.
To do so, architects had to adapt a
[music] new style.
Taloud tabo.
This style uses an inward sloping wall,
the tallude, to support a vertical slab
that's perpendicular to the ground
called [music] the table.
This technique created significant areas
of ornate facads that further serve the
state's propaganda.
The Federan pyramid was very innovative
at that time period because of the
integration of three-dimensional
sculptures with a building. Originally
uh those sculptures were painted with a
lot of different colors including green,
white, black and also yellow. Usually me
American pyramids were painted in just
one color. So I can imagine that those
viewers were impressed, highly impressed
because they had not seen the same thing
before. We think that those Teotakan
elites wanted to impress people by
inventing something new which is
associated with the new order
established with a with a building of
this pyramid
[music] carved out of heavy blocks of
andesite. The sculptures seem to float
on the sides of the building. An
illusory effect created by an ingenious
system.
In order to integrate three-dimensional
sculpture into the building, they
invented a new technology called tenon
sculpture. So here we see the serpent
head and this part is called a tenon.
[music]
>> In order to suspend the heavy rock,
a cantaliever on one end of the stone is
slid into a hole in the side of the
facade.
Within the pyramid, a chamber made of
heavy stone holds up the sculpture by
counterbalancing its weight.
So that sculpture does not fall. This
was unique in Mesa and we don't see the
same technology before [music] and
after.
Previously conducted in a highly
intimate setting within the tunnel, the
rituals for the transmission of power
now took place in public.
To that end, the pyramid of the [music]
feathered serpent was incorporated into
an architectural complex of over 160,000
m designed as an enormous stage, La
Citadela.
Surrounded by a 9-meter high platform,
this [music] closed, watertight space
was made to carry out an incredible
spectacle at the arrival of the rainy
season.
The myth we're told about ancient times,
which no one can remember, was that
there was only water, only the sea at
first. Thanks to divine intervention, a
sacred mountain rose up from the sea.
That moment marked the start of the
calendar and the passing of time.
We have proof that the Teotu Aaganos
flooded the square. It was their way of
representing the primitive sea from
which the sacred mountain had arisen.
More than just a city, Teayotiwakan now
embodied a myth. The original place
where the universe was created.
Its influence [music] stretched far and
wide from the Maya lands in the south to
the northernmost limits of the Mexican
territory.
An empire the size of which would
forever remain unmatched in Meso
America. Everyone thought Teayotiwakan
had become the supreme [music] city.
The square was huge. According to our
calculations, around 100,000 people must
have participated in the rituals.
We think it wasn't simply a ritual to
mark the passing of power among leaders
in Toouan. [music]
It might have also been used by other
governments and perhaps even Maya kings
who came here when it was their turn to
be anointed.
>> Ruler of Copan, pilgrim to Tetiwakan to
become enthroned as king of [music]
Copan. Kinish Kukmo was at Tetiwakan and
went back and became the ruler of Copan.
So it was an important voyage, a
religious voyage to create your identity
as the ruler himself.
>> In five [music] centuries, Teayoti Wakan
had in turns become a popular pilgrimage
site, then the biggest city in Meso
America, and finally an empire.
a city built by hundreds of thousands of
men from all over Central America.
All convinced they were carrying out the
work of the gods.
And yet in 650 [music]
AD, although no major construction had
been undertaken in over two centuries,
dissident voices seemed to rise over the
city.
Here
we're standing at the intersection of
multiple streets.
You can see the sides of various
residential complexes.
Suddenly, the roads were made narrower
and surveillance buildings were put into
place to control who could access the
various complexes.
It seems like the elite were trying so
hard to control the lowerass people that
the latter probably began to rebel.
We think that conflict began to grow
between the two social classes.
[music]
The repressive measures provoked the
anger of the Teoti Wakanos. [cheering]
A wave of violence started to spread in
the city streets.
[cheering]
It was violent. There's a lot of burning
and particularly I'm talking about the
ceremonial center, right? We have a lot
of evidence of burning in various areas.
So I do think it had to do with a
collapse with the central authority
itself.
That is probably quite spectacular
because think about the scale and these
are not wooden structures, right? So it
would have required a lot of planning
and a lot of resources to complete the
level of burning that we see in the city
itself. [music]
>> The elite overthrown Teayoti Wakan
became no more than an empty shell and
its religious center [music] collapsed
into a pile of ashes.
the city's residents fled.
>> We have proof that certain places were
abandoned very suddenly. We found
grindstones that they used to grind
grain.
And when we removed them, there was
still cornmeal residue on them. The
people must have fled quickly, leaving
behind anything heavy, taking with them
only what they could carry. The migrants
who had been living in Teodi Wakan
returned to their native homelands,
taking with them the sole prestige that
came with having lived in the greatest
and most powerful city that had ever
existed in Meso America.
>> Deserted, Teati Wakan fell into oblivion
for centuries.
But this incredible city has not
finished telling its story. Rediscovered
by the Aztecs in the 13th century, it's
become a place that [music] touches
anyone lucky enough to visit its great
pyramids.
After all, Teati Wakan is the birthplace
of the gods.
Heat. Heat.